Letter to the reader: initially composed, Sunday the 16th of October 2022.
As an ability to state somebody else's viewpoint, try treating my viewpoint as your journey from A to Z, where every identifiable port of call cannot be seen in isolation to the overall pattern and sequence.
I will specify that money is only not worthless money if it can purchase the effect of the performance of human labour.
I shall adduce evidence of how any form of taxation which comprises a component part of the money-price of a commodity is inflationary, and makes money worth less than before.
Thus the more they tax in a way which is not PET, (personal expenditure tax) the more worthless money becomes.
You may state that forms of taxation other than PET does not have this effect, but I would disagree with your belief that what you believe is true.
Some people believe that Adam Smith based wealth on gold. He most categorically did not.
He promoted the absence of tax upon trade, or more properly he showed that taxing it made money less efficient at commanding the purchase of the performance of human labour.
He opposed trade tariffs and excise duties; although to be fair to opposing points of view, he did concede that these were ways of obtaining revenue for the sovereign, i.e. the crown.
I often find I am standing on quick-sand when trying to get acknowledgement of my points.
It is as though the debater is treating each statement I make as an isolated entity, and never tries to stop challenging these.
But the effect of this inability to concede any ground has a disorientating effect upon me.
It is as though the debater unwittingly is participating within a discussion in the same format as Putin's state TV: which was to continually move on to something different in order to disprove the establishment of any kind of truth or foundation.
I am aware that some people are unaware that they are doing this.
The inability to offer any kind of academic concession would render the reader unable to disagree in a meaningful way, because in such an event the reader would never have repeated or accurately stated what I believe.
It is possible to offer support while disagreeing, but we are often unable to disagree properly.
Yours truly, David Roderick.