Introduction part two, the psychology of money.
I shall adumbrate that when the price of money is considered in the modern world, the psychology
of this evaluation leads to an inverted understanding where the hidden reality will exist behind
our backs and be quite opposite to that which we think we understand.
I am going to use three concepts: price, cost and worth.
I shall first follow an understanding of the 20th century viewpoint of the word "price",
that of "cost" and that of "worth".
I shall show how any of these concepts differed in Adam Smith's day from the present moment.
I shall define a few things here now.
If I have ten apples, then the price of ten apples in apples is, well, ten apples.
The cost of ten apples is ten apples, and the worth of ten apples is ten apples.
Likewise, if I have £100 in money, the price of this money is £100, the cost of this money
is £100, and the worth of this money is £100. No problem so far.
Here, I have implicitly defined the cost of apples in apples, and the worth of apples in apples.
Now, imagine a see-saw, or in America a teeter-totter. At the centre pivot is a label, and that label
says "price". On the left-hand side, as we view the see-saw, is ten apples.
On the right-hand side of the see-saw is £1, in money.
So, we can say that the price of ten apples was £1: "was" because it shall change in a moment.
Now, the price of apples doubles. So, now ten apples cost £2.
Previously, ten apples were worth £1.
Now, after the transformation, ten apples are worth £2.
What was a ratio of apples to money of one-to-one has now become a ratio of apples to
money of one to two.
What was a one to one ratio, if ten apples can be considered as one unit, and one pound
can be considered as one unit, has now become a one-to-two ratio.
Draw a table please.
We have on the columns, apples then money, going from left to right. And in the rows, we have
apples and money, going top to bottom.
This is a table of price.
Now, we've evaluated the ratio of apples to money as one-to-two: which is after the transformation.
Please write in the north-east cell of the table, the transformed ratio as one-to-two.
Now, let us consider what happens if we put money on the left side of the see-saw, and apples
on the right side of the see-saw. The central pivot still has a label that says price.
So, we are basically inverting what we are doubling.
So, previously we doubled the price of apples; now we double the price of money.
But, wait a minute, you might be saying: the price of money doesn't make any sense, because
the price of money has to be evaluated in money. But I said the Universe will exist
behind our backs.
I say the exchangeable price is however much it will swap for, of any commodity: in this
case it's apples.
But the 20th century psychological viewpoint does not concur with this, my viewpoint, when
we consider the price of money.
Our erstwhile condition, which is our previous set of circumstances, is that the one pound
will exchange for ten apples. So, the exchangeable amount of money is one pound, and this will
swap by ten apples on the market previously.
By the 20th-century viewpoint, when the price of money doubles, this infers that the amount
of money required doubles.
Money doubles.
So, now, two pounds will exchange for ten apples. This is the same as saying that one pound
of money will exchange for five apples.
This is because the ten apples will now cost two pounds.
So, if I have one pound, which will exchange for ten apples, and the price of this one pound
doubles, then one pound will exchange for five apples, because two pounds will exchange
for ten.
It is the exchangeable price of this pound which has risen.
More of it will be required: more pounds will be required to exchange for the commodity,
which is apples, than before.
So, one pound has just transformed to two pounds, where the units of apples remains the same.
I really must stress again that this is the 20th century viewpoint about what happens
by a change in the price of money.
It does not concur with the 18th-century viewpoint.
So in the south-west cell of our price table, we have a ratio of two-to-one: that is two
units of money to one units of apple.
Recall that in the north-east cell of the table, we had one unit of apple to two units
of money.
So far, our table is syntactically inconsistent. But it doesn't matter what we pay in, we get
the same result.
We are dealing with exchangeable amounts.
If I have a Rolex watch, the price of which I am selling for twenty thousand pounds. And
if I have four hundred Casio watches, the price of which each is fifty pounds.
And if I now abandon money altogether, and use a direct bartering scheme, I may swap four
hundred of my Casio watches for one of your Rolex watches.
Now, if the price of my Rolex watch increases, then fewer Rolex watches will swap by four
hundred Casio watches: which is the same thing as saying that more Casio watches will swap
by one Rolex watch.
Returning to the evaluation in terms of money, if your Rolex watch has transformed in price
from twenty thousand pounds to thirty thousand pounds, then, after this transformation, it will
swap by six hundred of my fifty pound Casio watches.
Now, let us call your Rolex ten apples.
What is in a name?
Would not a rose by any other name still smell as sweet?
It doesn't matter what we call the variable.
Ten apples is one unit -- is the name for one Rolex as one unit.
And let my four hundred Casio's be called "one pound" as a unit. Thus, if the price of
your ten apples doubles, it will now exchange by two pounds of money.
The ratio as the amounts has transformed from a ratio of one-to-one into a ratio of one
-to-two, where the apples were placed on the left-hand side of the see-saw.
No problem so far.
Now, let your Rolex be called one pound in money. And let my four hundred Casios be
called "ten apples".
When your Rolex doubles in price, it requires more Casios to exchange by it:
it requires eight hundred Casios.
But wait a minute. Your Rolex was called "one pound". So, surely, if one pound would double
in price, then it would require twenty apples to be exchanged for it by the eighteenth-century
viewpoint; not five apples to be exchanged for it by the twentieth-century viewpoint.
This viewpoint is non-intuitive to the modern interpretation.
What I am saying is that by the eighteenth-century viewpoint, the price of a commodity
is the amount of something else which will exchange by this commodity.
The mistake we made was to say that when the price of money doubles, the amount of money
becomes transformed into itself doubling.
By the eighteenth-century viewpoint, when the price of money doubles, the amount of
money becomes transformed by itself halving.
Because the twentieth-century -- or is it the twenty-first century (?) -- point of view, is inconsistent,
We know it's incorrect.
Depending on where we place money -- is it on the left-hand side of the see-saw, or is apples
on the left-hand side of the see-saw (?) -- we get a different result.
We know that Adam Smith was correct because he's logically consistent.
The same format as the price table by the eighteenth-century viewpoint has the transformed
ratio of one-to-two in the north-east cell, and the transformed ratio of one-to-two in
the south-west cell.
The semantic meaning of the word as money does not alter the syntax of this table.
It does not alter the syntactical meaning.
The table is syntactically consistent in the eighteenth century.
This ends my discussion about the word as price.