Here follows a survey of 8 peoples' ideas about the relationship between taxation and
inflation.
Toward the following 8 people, Lewis, Alwyn, Carol, Lee, Rob, Dennis, Murry, and Sam, the
following 4 questions were asked, to which they responded according to their own insights,
beliefs and viewpoints pertaining to the subject of economic theory.
Question 1.
Is tax a force which reacts to inflation?
Question 2.
Does taxation cause inflation?
Question 3.
Does competition, e.g. Apple vs. Samsung, cause inflation?
Question 4.
Does the dynamic changes in the prices of goods, materials, production and transportation
cause inflation as a one-way process?
i.e. is it possible that the reverse, deflation, can ever happen because of these things?
I collate their answers in the form of yes and no in a table.
Where the answer is don't know or maybe or uncertain, I have indicated this with a question
mark.
Where the answer is not recorded, I have indicated this with a hyphen.
For question 1,
which was, is tax a force which reacts to inflation(?),
all of the participants, bar 2, said yes.
Alwin didn't know; and Sam said yes and no, it depends.
Lewis said the higher inflation is, the higher the price is, so government receives more
revenue in tax.
Alwyn said she doesn't know if inflation leads to a change in the rate of taxation,
or in the amount of revenue the government receives in tax.
Carol said inflation leads to the government adding more taxes.
Lee said inflation causes taxation which is different in each country.
Rob said yes, tax is a reactive force:
as the price of goods, materials, production, transportation costs, etc. changes dynamically,
these changes lead to responsive changes in tax.
If the prices of goods, transport, etc. stay the same, then the rate of taxation is not
altered by the government; it remains the same.
Dennis said the way taxation reacts to inflation is not direct:
the idea of setting the rate of taxes is to encourage or discourage general spending.
He says taxation and inflation are always related; so yes, inflation causes taxation.
Murry said yes, you can try to ease inflation by increasing taxes:
the theory is by taking money out of peoples' pockets they spend less money, meaning that
fewer things are being bought, so prices will come down, which in turn entices people to
purchase.
Murry said tax receipts will increase with inflation;
governments may reduce tax in times of inflation to prevent destitution;
if tax increases, Murry said demand decreases, leading to a slowing of inflation.
Sam's answer to the question, is tax a force which reacts to inflation(?) was, it depends.
Yes and no, he says.
He explains his reasoning in his answer to question 2.
Question 2 was: does taxation cause inflation?
The respondees answered this question in a way which disagreed with each other.
Lewis says yes, taxation causes inflation. Alwyn says yes, Carol says yes.
Initially Lee didn't know, but upon consideration he concluded yes.
Rob says no, taxation does not cause inflation. Dennis says no. Murray says yes; and Sam says
no.
Lewis's reasoning was: he doesn't know if tax causes inflation, but probably yes;
it puts the prices of goods higher because of the tax, and this is to give the government
more revenue.
Alwyn stated taxation causes inflation. Carol says it's supposed not to, but it does.
Lee's final answer was tax causes inflation: this is an open question; there are lots of
influences and factors.
Rob says quite categorically that taxation does not cause inflation.
He says that tax is a reactive force, not an inflationary force.
Rob says that inflation is a force which is caused by competition.
Dennis says taxation does not directly cause inflation.
Murry says it can do, yes.
He says as an aside, interest rates cause inflation.
He says that quantitative easing is a way of printing money, and it will take 30 or 40
years to pay for the quantitative easing which happened following the bank collapse of 2008.
Sam's more circumspect answers are: take the national deficit to be the excess of government
spending above the revenue received from taxation.
If taxation increases and government spending remains the same, then this has the effect
of reducing the deficit, thereby reducing government borrowing or increasing the national surplus --
where national surplus is the excess of government revenue above taxation.
Sam says, as demand remains the same, prices will stay the same, thus inflation won't increase.
But, if taxation increases too much, people will have less money to afford to buy things,
so demand will fall, leading to a fall in prices, i.e. deflation, or a decrease in inflation.
He says, if the government borrows more in order to spend, then this does cause inflation, because
demand will increase, leading to an increase in prices, thereby increasing inflation.
He says, if taxation falls, but spending remains the same, then the national deficit will become
increased, or the national surplus will become reduced.
He says, people will have, in this case, more money, elevating prices, which is inflationary.
But, if taxation falls, but government spending remains the same, this will increase the amount
of money people have to spend, elevating prices, which is inflationary, unless sufficient growth
happens to absorb this change.
Question 3 was: does competition cause inflation?
Our respondees answered as follows.
Lewis says yes.
Alwyn yes.
Carol yes.
Lee, yes and no.
Rob yes.
Dennis no.
Murry yes and no.
Sam says no.
Lewis says yes:
competition causes inflation;
and his reasoning was, the more that manufacturers compete with each other, the more that they
produce, and in turn the more that they produce, the higher their costs are, and so in turn
they will charge more for their goods.
Alwyn who said yes:
competition does cause inflation; because when manufacturers compete with each other they
are putting up prices all the time.
She says, the best products are always sold for the highest prices.
Carol said yes.
I have not recorded an explanation.
Lee says yes and no.
He says that competition causes inflation, but the opposite can also happen;
but essentially the dynamic change of everything other than tax, causes inflation.
That was the viewpoint of Lee.
Rob says yes:
competition causes inflation.
He said the inflationary force is caused by competition.
He says: what changes the price of a house?
He says, the competition of people demanding houses, in conjunction with local political
opposition, resulting in no new housing, no new estates, and no new builds, increases the
price of houses.
He says, as the amount of land is a fixed quantity, this resource becomes depleted as population
growth expands.
He says the solution is to grow our economy by colonising other planets and solar systems.
Dennis said competition would not usually be cited to cause inflation unless it is with
respect to a global resource, and a monopoly is approached.
He says monopolies can certainly cause inflation, as can badly handled quantitative easing.
Murry says competition can cause inflation, but only does so where a monopoly exists; e.g.
if Apple buys Microsoft, this would lead to a massive control over the market.
He says, we can prevent this by promoting competition, which reduces prices.
He says, communism is a monopoly run by the state.
He says, what is important is the global markets, not national ones, when it comes to inflation.
Sam says, no, absolutely not: competition does not cause inflation. It reduces prices because
competition means, all else being equal, they compete on prices.
Question 4 was: does the dynamic changes in the prices of goods, material and production,
and transportation, cause inflation as a one-way process? i.e. is the reverse -- deflation --
ever possible because of these things?
I only have 3 answers recorded, because this question came as an after-thought, late in the
day within the survey.
The answers recorded are from Rob, Murry and Sam. Rob says, yes: deflation can happen.
Murry says no; and Sam says no. Rob says growth leads to employment, leading
to the supply of goods and services exceeding the demand for them.
He cites: if two different companies are competing, one tries to under-cut the other on prices.
He says, economic activity leads to the supply exceeding the demand.
He says if £2 million in revenue are attained by one company, then it can afford to under-cut
its smaller competitors, which might only receive £50,000 in revenue.
He says, the smaller competitor goes bust, and now the larger company has a monopoly, and
so can charge what it likes.
He says, business loves monopoly, so competition is ultimately inflationary as its longer-term
consequence.
Murray says, deflation can happen because of dynamic changes in the prices of goods, materials,
and production, and transportation.
For example, an event such as a war might lead to the price of petrol becoming elevated.
This is inflationary, whereas a surfeit of raw materials would lead to their price falling
except in the case of an oligarchy or monopoly.
He says, if labour costs rise, or the cost of iron ore increases, or if the prices of fuel
increases, then these events are massively inflationary.
The government may then attempt to bring down inflation by relying on the central bank to
vary its interest rates, and also by taxing more, and spending less.
The theory Murry explained to me, was that an increase in national surplus, or a decrease
in the national deficit, would have the consequence of people having less money to afford to buy
things, so demand would fall, leading to a fall in prices.
When I say people have less money, this was implying that they have less money in their
pockets, as they have been taxed more.
Murray continued that another government might borrow money, and use this money to pay salaries
to stimulate growth and development.
On the subject of whether deflation can happen,
Sam says deflation has happened in Japan recently.
It happens when there is an excess supply of some kind and demand remains the same, or
when there is a decrease in demand for some reason, e.g. after the Second World War, the
shortage of people led to a reduction in demand, enabling the government to spend more, without
causing inflation.
He says, if there are countries reliant upon one specific form of goods for export i.e.
oil, then if the global price of oil falls, then less oil is exported, and this will lead
to a reduction in the ability of people within that country to make purchases both domestically
and internationally, i.e. their general demand will have fallen.