I am the harbinger of economic prosperity, Long heft I forebeared, To bring about peace;
and forebode Trust between brethren and kith; Not passage to degeneracy.
I am the architect of a better tomorrow, I can see the past fore-told, To shine upon
an archaic monolith. Besmote with feelings, kind and old.
I am the wind of fortunes passing, I am the kind of smiling, laughing.
I shall be kind to little old ladies, Telling me stories of ever-so old.
I was not before the arcane angels, I was in better to bring about fortune. I am an
apple-seed grazing in past-time, Indigo fortune of ever-so old.
Ladies and footmen and fortunes and passing, Inter-twine features of pastures and laughing.
I see the angels with myriad faces, Intestine feelings of interlaced spaces. Voters, and
coasters, and railway sleepers, Dreary believers of myriad stations.
National heroes and nationalist graces, Are enmity to our saviour-faces.
Are you incumbent upon our noble races?
Are you insiders of indigo spaces?
Voters are not avoidant of laughter. Wisdom shall not be banished hereafter.
My insiders are never without though, Eating that apple that I never let grow.
Beaten brows and beaten frowns, Shall ne'er let the saviour crown, His horse to be dead of
course, Nor kingdom to be heard of hoarse.
My nonchalance pose and my broken throws, Shall mimic the apes of discourse; and toes To be
upon the party-line, which Shall be towed, like trawlers cold.
I say, what does all this mean?
I say, did Jack eat that bean?
When shall the future be here?
Whence shall the saviour-face appear?
Who shall not that very angel be?
Who is alive, and who is free?
Not the craven, nor the dead.
To progress, shall we put our bed: Our homestead raven, our property, Our slaves to freedom,
our enmity, To change, the presage of the past; Not futures known, nor even cast.
I am the bard, now follow me. Emancipation. Liberty.
The knee shall grow; The slaves are gone. The sun shine forth to evening song.
The mistakes are yet made by man, Who can be blind to his every can. Or can't, not knowing
what to do. If evening comes, I'll be anew, To porridge of the idle soup, Not ever-more
in an awful loop.
Just read. Just let the words ring true. Just be like me. Just see it through!