I now quote directly from chapter 24 of Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire by Edward Gibbon.
The removal of Saint Babylas excited an implacable opposition to the person of Julian.
His subjects complained with superstitious indignation that famine had pursued the emperor's steps
from Constantinople to Antioch; and the discontent of a hungry people was exasperated by the
injudicious attempt to relieve their distress.
The inclemency of the season had affected the harvests of Syria; and the price of bread,
in the markets of Antioch, had naturally risen in proportion to the scarcity of corn.
But the fair and reasonable proportion was soon violated by the rapacious arts of monopoly.
In this unequal contest, in which the produce of the land is claimed by one party as his
exclusive property, is used by another as a lucrative object of trade, and is required
by a third for the daily and necessary support of life; all the profits of the intermediate
agents are accumulated on the head of the defenceless consumers.
The hardships of their situation were exaggerated and increased by their own impatience and
anxiety; and the apprehension of a scarcity gradually produced the appearances of a famine.
When the luxurious citizens of Antioch complained of the high price of poultry and fish, Julian
publicly declared that a frugal city ought to be satisfied with a regular supply of wine,
oil, and bread; but he acknowledged that it was the duty of a sovereign to provide for
the subsistence of his people.
With this salutary view, the emperor ventured on a very dangerous and doubtful step, of fixing
by legal authority, the value of corn.
He enacted that, in a time of scarcity, it should be sold at a price which had seldom
been known in the most plentiful years; and that his own example might strengthen his
laws, he sent into the market 422,000 modii, or measures, which were drawn by his order
from the granaries of Hierapolis, of Chalcis and even of Egypt.
The consequences might have been foreseen and were soon felt.
The Imperial wheat was purchased by the rich merchants;
the proprietors of land, or of corn, withheld from the city the accustomed supply; and the
small quantities that appeared in the market were secretly sold at an advanced and illegal
price.
Julian still continued to applaud his own policy, treated the complaints of the people
as a vain and ungrateful murmur, and convinced Antioch that he had inherited the obstinacy,
though not the cruelty, of his brother Gallus.
The remonstrances of the municipal senate served only to exasperate his inflexible mind.
He was persuaded, perhaps with truth, that the senators of Antioch who possessed lands,
or were concerned in trade, had themselves contributed to the calamities of their country;
and he imputed the disrespectful boldness which they assumed to the sense, not of public
duty, but of private interest.
The whole body, consisting of 200 of the most noble and wealthy citizens, were sent under
a guard from the palace to the prison; and, though they were permitted, before the close
of evening, to return to their respective houses, the emperor himself could not obtain
the forgiveness which he had so easily granted.
The same grievances were still the subject of the same complaints, which were industriously
circulated by the wit and levity of the Syrian Greeks.
During the licentious days of the Saturnalia, the streets of the city resounded with insolent
songs, which derided the laws, the religion, the personal conduct, and even the beard of
the emperor; and the spirit of Antioch was manifested by the connivance of the magistrates
and the applause of the multitude.