Message to a friend 10th September 2023:
Did you know that the pagan Roman emperor Julian fixed the price of corn by law in Antioch?
Then he tried to supply the market with corn at this price,
either from the state or via assets which he had control over.
The landowners being a monopoly or oligarchy simply withheld the supplying of corn to the
market thus elevating the price, preferring to store it for the next year instead.
Julian had all the landowners, the senate of Antioch, arrested and incarcerated for a very
small amount of time before he forgave them and let them go free again. State control in this way
reminds me of something akin to Soviet Russia, which caused a lot of starvation, especially
in the Ukraine. I see occasionally posters for communism put on walls in York, but these
are usually pulled down or defaced in a short time. A year earlier, on Friday the 21st October 2022,
I wrote to my friend, having completed my first pass of Keynes's general theory,
he has introduced me to Mummery and Hobson's Physiology of Industry 1889, which is wonderfully
written if in error in places. Each model depends upon underlying assumptions,
and political economy is about discerning truth within those.
Re: Orwell's comments about another author, like Nero playing the fiddle while Rome was burning,
but playing it with his face turned towards the flames, I recalled that Orwell said this
about Henry Miller, who wrote Tropic of Cancer and Tropic of Capricorn in the 1930s or thereabouts.
I say this because I perceive Western civilization as already reached the beginning of its end,
and the situation is very grave. A model based upon flawed underlying assumptions can be more
complex than, for example, no model at all. It can then produce a prediction which matches
an observation by incorrect reasons, a type 3 error, and become much feted, but nevertheless wrong
though. Very easy to get bogged down in a myriad of functions and statistics without knowing what
is relevant to be sought.