Now I shall talk about the word as "cost".
We put apples on the left side of the see-saw, and money on the right-hand side.
Now, the cost of 10 apples was £1.
The cost of apples doubles.
Now, the cost of 10 apples is £2.
Please draw a table, the same as the one you drew before.
From left to right, the columns are apples and money.
From top to bottom, the rows are apples and money, in that order.
Now, we fill in the north-east cell.
The ratio of one-to-one has been transformed into a ratio of one-to-two, apples to money.
So far, so good.
We now investigate whether the cell in the south-west position is identical,
i.e. does it have a ratio of one-to-two after the transformation,
when we invert the position of apples and money on the see-saw?
We shall now put money on the left-hand side of the see-saw, and apples on the right.
We investigate, using psychological words, linguistic possibilities.
The cost of £1 is 10 apples.
This is previous to any change.
Now, after the change, the cost of money doubles.
How many apples can £1 now purchase?
I must point out that cost is not the cost of borrowing money from any central bank, or subsidiary bank.
But we're treating the cost of £1 as a commodity in comparison to the cost of say $1 as a commodity.
Treat money sterling like the cost of any commodity.
An economist might say something like: the interest rate increases, reducing the cost of money;
and the price of it should go down depending upon a demand curve.
But we're not talking about anything of the sort.
We're saying that where money is, say, a banana, the cost of one banana is 10 apples, previously.
And if the cost of a banana doubles, how many apples can one banana now purchase?
I'll give you time to pause to think about this.
Well, the 20th century, the 21st century viewpoint, and the explanation of it, is that, previously, £1
would buy 10 apples; so, the cost of each apple was 10 pence.
And if the cost of money doubles, subsequently the cost of any apple becomes 20 pence.
So, we can only buy five of them after this transformation in cost.
So, what do we have in our south-west cell in our cost table?
Well, if £1 can buy 10 apples previously, and only five after,
that's the same as saying that £2 will buy 10 apples after.
So, our ratio, from one-to-one money to apples, has become a ratio of two-to-one money to apples.
But this is inconsistent with our north-east cell.
Again, we have an inconsistency in the 20th century
linguistic understanding: which is purely psychological, which exists entirely in our heads,
and nowhere in external reality.
So, we can already conclude that the 20th century viewpoint about the word "cost" is wrong.
It is inconsistent: therefore it can't be true.
The ratio is inverted depending on which position we put apples, and which position we put
money, on which side of the see-saw. It is asymmetric.
We don't have a symmetrical ratio within the given transformation.
Now, the mystery is to examine which cell is correct:
is it the north-east cell, or is it the south-west cell?
To do this, we will need to examine the 18th century viewpoint,
and hopefully it will be consistent. If it is consistent, we know it to be true;
and this will reveal which one of our cells is the external reality.
Please note that in the table for the 18th century price,
both the south-west cell, and the north-east cell, have become transformed to
the same ratio, which is one-to-two:
that is one-to-two of the left-hand side to the right-hand side.
It didn't matter whether we place apples, or money, on the left-hand side: we got the same result.
The semantic meaning of the word "money" didn't change that in the 18th century.
We note that it did in the 20th century, previously.
I posit that
the correct cell for the cost in the 20th century is the north-east cell.
It's merely a speculation at this stage; and the reason I say that is because
we have a seemingly non-absurd transformed ratio
of one-to-two, apples to money, left-hand side to the right-hand side.
I believe that words, and concepts, should have clearly definable
meanings, as, indeed, should prepositions within sentences.
I note that the prepositions within the English language have become very chaotic,
and this transitional change within linguistics has occurred beginning of
Victorian times, right through the 20th century, up until the present day.
To examine the concept of money further,
let us consider what money could have been thought of during most of the Iron Age,
which was maybe a pound of iron ore, smelted from some mine.
So, I'd like to examine the north-east cell first.
The transformed ratio of the cost of apples, to the cost of money:
which I've speculated, as a hypothesis, that it should be
one-to-two, apples to money,
exchangeable amount of; which is after the transformation.
This makes linguistic sense as a concept, both in the 20th century, and indeed in the 18th century,
because the cost of something is the amount on the right-hand side of the see-saw,
when we put the something on the left-hand side.
That is, if 10 apples on the left-hand side would cost one pound of iron ore on the right-hand side;
then, if the cost of apples doubles, then we now require two pounds of iron ore to exchange
by 10 apples. To put it another way,
10 apples to exchange by two pounds of iron ore.
Recall that we are treating iron as money: pounds of iron as money.
Now invert these positions: put money, which is iron, on the left-hand side of the see-saw,
and put apples on the right-hand side of the see-saw.
So, we are saying that one pound of iron exchanges by 10 apples; and subsequent to a transformation,
the cost of iron doubles.
So, we can infer linguistically that whatever is on the right-hand side of the see-saw, which is apples,
is now going to be required in double the amount to exchange
for what is on the left-hand side of the see-saw: which is one pound of iron.
So when the pound of iron, cost of, doubles, we now exchange by 20 apples.
This is the 18th century viewpoint, and it is logically consistent.
It is semantically consistent, and it is syntactically consistent.
Money doesn't do anything special semantically to the syntax of the see-saw.
It is symmetrical. So, the 18th century is correct; and my erstwhile hypothesis, which was that
what is on the right-hand side of the see-saw doubles in amount, by the word "cost", when the
cost doubles, of the substance on the left-hand side, seems sound.
Recall I previously mentioned that the word "price"
doubles the amount on the right-hand side.
Now, we can infer that the word "cost" doubles the amount that's on the right-hand side.
We're forming a pretty picture, so far.
But what is concerning is that the word "cost" in the 20th century is inconsistent.
So, when we use the words "cost of money", or, indeed, the more modern syntax,
which is the words as "cost to money",
we are not hitting reality in the correct place:
we're deluding ourselves, because when money is treated as a commodity, we fail.
Money is no different to any other commodity, as an external reality, I say, anyway.
Here ends my discussion of the word as "cost".