In the following quotation from Adam Smith's Wealth of Nations, when the author uses the
words as "nominal price", he has previously defined this to be the price in money which
is paid. The quotation is taken from book 1, chapter 11, part 3, which is
titled: "Digression concerning the variations in the value of silver
during the course of the four last centuries." Recall that this book was
published in the 1770s; so, the four last centuries are from 1300 onwards. I
quote: "But the nominal sum which constitutes the market price of every
commodity, is necessarily regulated, not so much by the quantity of silver which
according to the standard ought to be contained in it, as by that which it is
found by experience actually is contained in it. This nominal sum
therefore is necessarily higher when the coin is much debased by clipping and
wearing, than when near to its standard value." End quote. Smith here is inferring
that when the coin contains less silver than freshly minted silver coin, its
worth, and hence Smith's understanding of its cost, is less.
Hence money has now decreased in price.
Note that in our previous examples, where we put the commodity under question on
the left side of the see-saw, and then doubled its price, or doubled its cost,
or doubled its worth, that when its price doubled, by the 18th century viewpoint,
its cost doubled, and its worth doubled. And when its cost doubled, that is the
cost of the item on the left-hand side of the see-saw, the ratio of one-to-one was
transformed into a ratio of one-to-two: that is, the left-hand side of the see-saw
to the right-hand side of the see-saw.
In the 18th century viewpoint, when the cost halves, the worth also halves.
We can infer that if the cost doubled, the ratio of one-to-one transformed into a
ratio of one-to-two, left to right. But what is a ratio? It signifies the amount
of something: the quantity of the item to be exchanged.
Where the price doubled, the cost doubled. Where the price doubled, the worth
doubled. The cost, and the worth, were equivalent by the 18th century viewpoint.
So, likewise, if the price were to half, the cost would halve, thereby also halving
the worth.
Let us say that a bushel of wheat, instead of being paid for in freshly minted
coin, is paid for in debased, clipped, worn coin.
So, a bushel of wheat now costs more money because you need more of those coins
stamped with a specific, clipped, and worn denomination in money, to acquire
a fixed weight of silver. This presumes of course that the ratio between freshly
minted silver coin, and bushels of wheat, remains unaltered.
A specific, stamped, denomination of this worn, or clipped, silver coin affords fewer items of
bushels of wheat because it will purchase less wheat. Therefore, a bushel of wheat now costs more money.
Adam Smith did not think about money, or rationalise its price, and cost, in the same
way that a 20th century individual did. The 20th century economist is a 20th
century individual, and may very well believe that if the price of money rises
that more money will exchange by a fixed number of bushels of wheat: thus, also
believing that if the price of money falls, that less money will exchange by a fixed number of
bushels of wheat. The 20th century viewpoint is not that of the 18th century: which is that if the price
of money falls, its cost decreases, and hence more money will exchange by the same amount of wheat;
so less wheat can be had for the same amount of money.
To see this pictorially, imagine a vertical scale consisting of the amount of something.
Previously, so much money, the amount of which is fixed, exchanges by the amount as say 10
bushels of wheat. After the price of money falls, the amount of money which will exchange by 10
bushels of wheat increases. So, the ratio has become altered: more money, a greater amount of it, is
required to exchange by 10 bushels of wheat. So, 10 bushels of wheat will exchange by more money:
which is the same as saying, that, for a fixed amount of money, fewer bushels of wheat, less than 10,
will exchange by this fixed amount of money, after the price of money has fallen.