When the King of France invaded Holland in 1672, the owners of bank money were keen to
buy receipts at any price so they could bury the bullion in their gardens, after withdrawing
it from the Bank of Amsterdam.
As a consequence of this calamity, every merchant found that in order to purchase receipts he,
or she, was required to spend a lot more, say, bushels of corn, or the worth of bushels of
corn, upon these receipts.
Say, previously, one gilder would exchange by 30 bushels of corn.
After this calamity, or during the calamity, one gilder may exchange for 300 bushels of
corn: that is one gilder in bank money.
Smith wrote, "The enemy, informed of the constitution of the bank, might even buy them [the receipts -ed] up in order
to prevent the carrying away of the treasure.
In such emergencies, the bank, it is supposed, would break through its ordinary rule of making
payment only to the holders of receipts."
Smith continued, "The holders of receipts, who had no bank money, must have received within
2 or 3% of the value of the deposit for which their respective receipts had been granted."
Smith continued, "The bank, therefore, it is said, would in this case make no scruple of
paying, either with money or bullion, the full value of what the owners of bank money, who
could get no receipts, were credited for in its books;
paying, at the same time, 2 or 3% to such holders of receipts as had no bank money, that being
the whole value which, in this state of things, could justly be supposed due to them."
Further, Smith said, "In 1672, when the French king was at Utrecht, the bank of Amsterdam
paid so readily, as left no doubt of the fidelity with which it had observed its engagements.
Some of the pieces which were then brought from its repositories, appeared to have been
scorched with a fire which happened in the town-house soon after the bank was established.
Those pieces, therefore, must have lain there from that time."
Smith again, "The Bank of Amsterdam professes to lend out no part of what is deposited with
it, but for every gilder for which it gives credit in its books, to keep in its repositories
the value of a gilder either in money or bullion. That it keeps in its repositories all the money
or bullion for which there are receipts in force for which it is at all times liable to be called upon,
and which in reality is continually going from it, and returning to it again, cannot well be doubted."
And further, Smith said, "At Amsterdam, however, no point of faith is better established than that,
for every gilder circulated as bank money, there is a correspondent gilder
in gold or silver to be found in the treasures of the bank.
The city is guaranteed that it should be so."