Introduction -- part 3. The Bank of Amsterdam.
The Bank of Amsterdam was established in the year 1609, in response to a problem which
emerged in small states, such as Genoa, or Hamburg, whereby the local currency was not
desirable for international trade, i.e. merchants did not wish to use it, and in preference
they elected to use coins of neighbouring states which were more internationally recognised,
and accepted, in foreign trade. In particular, coins such as the Mexico
dollars was well trusted to have a specific well-known amount of silver of an ascertained
purity. This was important because these coins, if so desired, could be melted down,
and formed into bullion, or items such as trinkets, jewellery, snuff boxes, etc.
People knew exactly how much silver was contained in a Mexico dollar, so it would have been
more effective as a durable, portable thing, desirable in exchange, for which other commodities
could be exchanged, i.e. bought. To addle this, there were also French crowns,
Dutch guilders, and stivers, English silver coin, Ducatoons, Rix dollars, Portuguese
coin, new Louis d'ors, old Louis d'ors, Ducats, among others. If a small state chose to reform
its currency, melt down the old coin, and cast the gold or silver into new coin, while altering
the ratio of precious metal to other metal, then this would not alter the fact that merchants
did not wish to use this national currency in international trade. The myriad coins which
were used in international trade each weighed something different to each other, and each
had a different alleged purity of precious metal, which could not be guaranteed and ascertained
without melting the coin down. Frauds might emerge where a coin had less gold than promised,
and a merchant is an expert in trade, not in coins and metallurgy. He, she, one, needed
some banking system whereby a fixed, known, quantity of gold, of guaranteed purity, could
be reliably exchanged, readily. Prior to the introduction of paper money, which was originally
instituted by numerous domestic commercial banks, unlike the Bank of Amsterdam; and prior
to the institution of banks for international trade, like the Bank of Amsterdam, payments
made by smaller merchants were orchestrated by what was called a merchant bill, drawn upon
a large reputable trader, by an agent of this trader, for an additional fee. The system worked
as follows. A small factory, or trader, in Manchester, wishes to lend some stock to a larger reputable
merchant in London, such as a large wholesaler, or a large retailer. Both parties wish this
vendible stock to be sold on to the consumer. This merchant in London is deemed trustworthy.
And this trustworthy wholesaler in London does not pay upfront for this advanced stock,
but draws up a bill of exchange, also known as a merchant's bill, which is an agreement
that this large trustworthy firm will pay it within six months time, from hence.
The small factory, or trader, in Manchester, is the supplier of stock.
The larger reputable merchant in London has a debt to the small manufacturer in Manchester.
Within six months time it is hoped that this stock has been sold to the consumer.
So, the smaller manufacturer, is owed a certain amount, say 10 gold sovereign coins.
This debt, this certificate as the merchant's bill, can be sold for nine and a half golden
sovereigns, if the Manchester merchant desires to lose the difference, for immediate money;
and the purchaser of this bill gains half a sovereign when the date of maturity arrives,
and this money becomes payable.
This is how the banking system operated before the establishment of banks where a trading
individual was facilitated to have the keeping of a bank account.
But here lay a subtle problem in international trade.
A reputable London merchant would pay in English silver coin, and a reputable Paris merchant would
pay in French silver coin.
If there would have been more silver contained in the total weight of a certain number of
English coin, in comparison with the total weight of a certain number of French coin,
then it would be more profitable, for a merchant to obtain a bill upon a reputable London merchant,
than a reputable French merchant.
So this would encourage a French manufacturer to sell his stock in England, rather than in France;
and also would encourage the English manufacturer to sell his stock in England, rather than in France.
As a consequence, silver would leave England, and be taken to France.
Silver, i.e. money, or cash, or hard currency today, always gravitates towards the place
where industrious labour is being performed:
for which stock is required, capital or material stock, to generate profit,
and hence to employ workers within a profitable enterprise.
But that is an aside for the present moment within this discussion.
If more silver is obtained in England, than in France,
the exchange is said to favour France,
and is against England: whereby the French merchant is said to gain a premium,
which is paid by the London merchant; and silver leaves England for France.
Contrary to this, if more silver would be obtained in France than in London,
then the French merchant who obtains English silver is said to give a premium,
and the exchange is said to favour England, and be against France.
This is the theory.
In reality, before the reformation of the English silver coin in King William's time, 1696,
the worth of the English coin was 25% below the worth of silver contained,
that it should have had, as these coins had often been clipped, and were also extremely worn.
The exchange between England and France was said to be 25% against France,
and hence in favour of England.
I like to remember this as: the exchange favours the vendor of actual material goods
if they are to be encouraged by an augmentation in the receipt of a higher amount of silver upon
payment. So, we have that in King William's time, the worth of English coin was 25% below
the worth of freshly minted silver coin; and because of this, the exchange between
England and France was said to be 25% in favour of England.
However, if the payment was made in English coin which was non-clipped, and non-worn,
the French manufacturer who cashed a merchant's bill upon a reputable London merchant, could
then obtain more silver than the calculated amount, i.e. what Smith called the real exchange,
which means the actual amount of pure silver contained within 10 specific coins,
may have been greater than the agreed amount, and hence the French merchant exporting to London,
might get the premium.
If the French merchant could somehow select the better quality, newly freshly minted coin,
which had not been clipped or worn, then the French merchant would obviously obtain
more silver than if the merchant had been paid in old, worn, clipped coin.
The Bank of Amsterdam was a formulation of a banking system for international trade,
which avoided ambiguities and variables.
So, let's now talk about the Bank of Amsterdam.