Part four, Promissory notes (which are paper money), and commercial banks.
Within Wealth of Nations, Book Two, Chapter Two, Of Money, Adam Smith wrote,
"Some years ago, the different banking companies of Scotland were in the practice of inserting into their bank notes what they called an optional clause; by which they promised payment to the bearer,
either as soon as the note should be presented, or, in the option of the directors, six months after such presentment, together with the legal interest for the said six months.
The directors of some of those banks sometimes took advantage of this optional clause, and sometimes threatened those who demanded gold and silver in exchange for a considerable number of their notes, that they would take advantage of it,
unless such demanders would content themselves with a part of what they demanded.
The promissory notes of those banking companies constituted, at that time, the far greater part of the currency of Scotland,
which this uncertainty of payment necessarily degraded below value of gold and silver money.
During the continuance of this abuse (which prevailed chiefly in 1762, 1763 and 1764), while the exchange between London and Carlisle was at par,
that between London and Dumfries would sometimes be four per cent. against Dumfries, though this town is not thirty miles distant from Carlisle.
But at Carlisle, bills were paid in gold and silver;
whereas at Dumfries, they were paid in Scotch bank notes; and the uncertainty of getting these bank notes exchanged for gold and silver coin, had thus degraded them, four per cent. below the value of that coin.
The same act of parliament, which suppressed ten and five shilling bank notes, suppressed likewise this optional clause,
and thereby restored the exchange between England and Scotland to its natural rate, or to what the course of trade and remittances might happen to make it."
(end quote).
Within the same chapter, Smith also said,
"It is not by augmenting the capital of the country, but by rendering a greater part of that capital active and productive than would otherwise be so, that the most judicious operations of banking can increase the industry of the country."
(end quote).
Maybe I read that passage too fast.
I repeat it here.
(quote).
(end quote).
Smith also said,
"When we compute the quantity of industry which the circulating capital of any society can employ,
we must always have regard to those parts of it only which consist in provisions, materials, and finished work;
the other, which consists in money, and which serves only to circulate those three, must always be deducted."
(end quote).
The quantity of money must always be deducted from the circulating capital,
Smith infers.
I understand this may be confusing.
I will address this confusion after finishing this quotation.
I quote,
"In order to put industry into motion, three things are requisite;
materials to work upon, tools to work with, and the wages or recompense for the sake of which the work is done.
Money is neither a material to work upon, nor a tool to work with;
and though the wages of the workmen are commonly paid to him in money,
his real revenue, like that of all other men, consists, not in the money, but in the money's worth;
not in the metal pieces, but in what can be got for them."
(end quote).
Now I will re-read this passage at a faster tempo.
"In order to put industry into motion, three things are requisite;
materials to work upon, tools to work with, and the wages or recompense for the sake of which the work is done.
Money is neither a material to work upon, nor a tool to work with;
and though the wages of the workmen are commonly paid to him in money,
his real revenue, like that of all other men, consists, not in the money, but in the money's worth;
not in the metal pieces, but in what can be got for them."
(end quote).
Smith tells us that circulating capital is composed of four parts:
one, provisions; two, materials; three, finished work; and four, money.
He tells us that only the first three -- provisions, materials, and finished work --
are useful in computing how much quantity of industry, i.e. the intelligent performance of human labour,
happens because of the circulating capital of any society.
He says we must disregard the part as money from the circulating capital if we are to look at how many people are currently employed.
Provisions might compose of electricity, oil, gas, water, fodder for my horse.
Materials may compose of flour for a baker, leather for a shoemaker.
And finished work may be the shoemaker's shoes, the breadmaker's bread.
Without finished work, no enterprise can sell its finished work, and so it cannot attain revenue,
and it cannot make profit out of its revenue.
Now for some basic definitions taken from Smith.
I will state what these are, as I believe I can achieve a greater level of didacism instead of quoting his work directly.
The words as "real wealth" mean something tangibly material, i.e. an actual item of value:
where the word "value" means the substance and form of an object which supplies the wants and pleasures of mankind,
as taken from Edward Gibbon, Decline and Fall, Chapter 71, Part 3.
So real wealth means something tangibly material, something I can possess,
something which is the product of the intelligent performance of human labour.
It does not consist of coin or notes necessarily, but in the worth that these coins or notes can be had in exchange by.
The words as "neat revenue" comprehend how much stuff gets to where it is needed to be consumed,
be that a house which becomes bought, or food, or clothes; but not a bridge, nor a road, nor a sewage system,
because these are not usually created by private individuals to be owned by specific parties.
The cost of labour is the worth of the wages that an employer pays to the employee.
The worth of these wages is the amount of real wealth which the employee may purchase by his wages.
His wages are his recompense for the labour he performs.
The price of labour is the amount of money that the employee is paid.
If the price of living is very high, the worker may live a hand-to-mouth existence,
i.e. she places the whole worth of her wages inside her stock reserved for immediate consumption.
I denote this by the phrase "hand-to-mouth wages".
If Wendy lives like this, in her case her whole wage forms part of the neat revenue of the society.
Excluding the possibility of nationalised production of coal, gas, electricity, telephony, etc. from our viewpoint,
as these all produce a vendible commodity -- coal, electricity, gas, steel, etc. --
all other forms of taxpayer spending, such as doctors, teachers, police, prison officers, judges, etc.,
don't produce something vendible.
And I say these public services, to avoid stymying the wealth of a nation,
should be paid for exclusively by the expense of one, and only one, form of taxation called PET: personal expenditure tax.
The reason why this is the case forms the subject matter of these three books further to this introduction.
If it be taken that stock and unfettered private initiative and enterprise, which is not necessarily the same thing as ownership,
causes businesses which produce vendible commodities,
then those businesses generate two forms of neat revenue.
First, is the part of the worker's wage, which the worker spends upon her stock reserved for immediate consumption;
within the case of Wendy: experiencing hand-to-mouth wages.
And the second part as neat revenue, which unfettered private initiative and enterprise generates,
is the actual stuff she produces as a consequence of her work, which is consumed by other people,
i.e. all commodities, shoes, corn, consumer electronics, houses, etc.
When a society within a nation builds a hospital or a bridge,
this comprehends part of the gross revenue of all inhabitants of that country.
It is not really consumed by anybody.
What is consumed is proportional to the neat revenue of all inhabitants of that country,
which is proportional to their real wealth: that which is tangible, and tangibly material;
an actual item of substance and form which supplies the wants and pleasures of mankind.
A house is a commodity, which comprehends part of the neat revenue of the inhabitants of a great country,
because the house initially was produced by private enterprise and initiative,
which I hasten to add is not the same concept as ownership.
And so when it got delivered to the consumer, who moved to the house (obviously it didn't move itself),
it was treated as a commodity.
When I say that unfettered private initiative and enterprise:
unfettered in an unchained sense
but within reasonably devised planning laws, and laws to prevent criminal activities such as drugs and guns;
when I refer to unfettered private initiative and enterprise being not necessarily the same thing as ownership,
and very different to the concept of ownership,
I might cite the example that a slave is owned,
but a slave's labour is not an example of private enterprise.
An argumentative person may tell me that the slave owner, or slave trader, was an example of private enterprise,
but I would reply to that by saying that the choice of labour which the slave performs is not that of private initiative,
but that of the slave being controlled by some type of a master, or a central planner.
In any case, whether slavery be achieved via economic controls written into law,
pertaining to taxation and land ownership,
or via the use of armaments and brute force, brutality and human rights abuses,
we can say that neither is the most perfect and obvious system of natural liberty.